<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Heroic poem upon His Majesties most gracious releasing the chimney-money</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 8 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43439</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1589</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R34456</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">14444322</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 14444322</idno>
            <idno type="VID">102352</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43439)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 102352)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1060:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Heroic poem upon His Majesties most gracious releasing the chimney-money</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 broadside.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Taylor ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLXXXIX [1689]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:102352:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>An Heroic POEM UPON HIS MAJESTIES Moſt GRATIOUS RELEASING the CHIMNEY-MONEY.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>ABove the Waves, ſo <hi>Neptune</hi> ſhew'd his Face,</l>
               <l>To chide the Winds and ſave the <hi>Trojan</hi> R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e;</l>
               <l>As our Great <hi>MONARCH</hi> has our Fears releas't,</l>
               <l>And threatning Storms of <hi>Tyranny</hi> ſuppres't.</l>
               <l>Our drooping Nation, almoſt quite become,</l>
               <l>The Prey of <hi>Lawleſs Power,</hi> and Cruel <hi>Rome</hi>;</l>
               <l>Shatter'd by <hi>Popiſh Plots,</hi> and <hi>Jeſuites</hi> Hate,</l>
               <l>Is now reſtor'd and made a Glorious State.</l>
               <l>The Seat of <hi>Empire,</hi> where muſt ſhortly come,</l>
               <l>The Rebel-<hi>Iriſh</hi> to receive their Doom;</l>
               <l>And now proud <hi>Rome</hi> by His Atchievements ſcar'd,</l>
               <l>(Although another <hi>Caeſar</hi> were her Guard)</l>
               <l>Could trembling wiſh behind more <hi>Alps</hi> to ſtand,</l>
               <l>While His freſh <hi>Laurels</hi> Her ſwift fall portend.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Sea's our own, and now all <hi>Nations</hi> greet,</l>
               <l>With loering Sails each Veſſel of our Fleet;</l>
               <l>Our <hi>Monarchs</hi> Power extends as far as Winds do blow,</l>
               <l>Or ſwelling Sails around the <hi>Globe</hi> may go.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Heaven that has plac'd this <hi>Iſland</hi> to give Law,</l>
               <l>To ballance <hi>Europe,</hi> and her <hi>States</hi> to aw;</l>
               <l>In this conjuncture does on <hi>Britain</hi> ſmile,</l>
               <l>The Greateſt <hi>Leader,</hi> and the Greateſt <hi>Ile.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whether this Portion of the World were rent,</l>
               <l>By the rude Ocean from the Continent</l>
               <l>Or thus Created, it was ſure deſign'd,</l>
               <l>To be the Sacred Refuge of Mankind.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Here the Oppreſſed ſhall henceforth reſort,</l>
               <l>Juſtice to crave, and Succour at our Court;</l>
               <l>And then our <hi>Soveraign,</hi> not for ours alone,</l>
               <l>But for the World's Great <hi>MONARCH</hi> ſhall be known.</l>
               <l>Fame ſwifter than his winged Navy flies,</l>
               <l>To every Land that near the Ocean lies;</l>
               <l>Sounding his Name, and telling dreadful News,</l>
               <l>To all that Tyranny, and Rapine uſe.</l>
               <l>While his bleſt Subjects, under their own Laws,</l>
               <l>Where no unjuſt controle can interpoſe;</l>
               <l>Enjoy in ample Liberty and Eaſe,</l>
               <l>With Freedom Plenty, and with Plenty Peace.</l>
               <l>Lords of the Worlds large waſt, the Ocean, we</l>
               <l>Whole Forreſts ſend to Rule upon the Sea;</l>
               <l>And every Coaſt may trouble or relieve,</l>
               <l>But none can viſit us. without His leave.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Our little World, the Image of the great,</l>
               <l>Like that amidſt the boundleſs Ocean Set;</l>
               <l>Of her own growth has all that Nature craves,</l>
               <l>And all that's ſcarce, as Tribute from the Waves.</l>
               <l>As <hi>AEgypt</hi> does not on the Clouds rely,</l>
               <l>But to her <hi>Nile</hi> ows more than to the <hi>Skie</hi>;</l>
               <l>So what our Earth, and what our Heaven denies,</l>
               <l>Our ever conſtant Friend (the <hi>Sea</hi>) ſupplies.</l>
               <l>The taſte of hot <hi>Arabia</hi>'s Spice we know,</l>
               <l>Free from the ſcorching heat that makes it grow;</l>
               <l>Without the Worm in <hi>Perſian</hi> Silk we ſhine,</l>
               <l>And without Planting, Drink of every Vine.</l>
               <l>Our's is the Harveſt where the <hi>Indians</hi> mow,</l>
               <l>We Plough the deep, and Reap what others ſow;</l>
               <l>Things of the Nobles't kind our own Soyl breeds,</l>
               <l>Stout are our <hi>Men,</hi> and Warlike are our <hi>Steeds.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rome,</hi> tho' her Eagle through the World had flown,</l>
               <l>Could never make this Iſland all her own;</l>
               <l>Here flouriſh'd <hi>Edward,</hi> and the <hi>Black Prince</hi> too,</l>
               <l>Victorious <hi>Henry,</hi> and now GREAT SIR, YOU,</l>
               <l>For YOU we ſtay'd, once more to fill our Story</l>
               <l>With great Atchievments, and with Acts of Glory.</l>
               <l>When for more Worlds the <hi>Macedonian</hi> cry'd,</l>
               <l>He wiſt not <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>etys</hi> in her lap did hide</l>
               <l>Another yet, a world reſerv'd for You,</l>
               <l>To make more Great, than that he did ſubdue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When <hi>Fate</hi> or <hi>Errour</hi> had our Age miſled,</l>
               <l>And on this Nation ſuch Confuſion ſpread,</l>
               <l>The only Cure which could from <hi>Heav'n</hi> come down</l>
               <l>Was ſo much <hi>power</hi> and <hi>Piety</hi> in <hi>One.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>One,</hi> whoſe Extraction from an Ancient Line,</l>
               <l>Gives Hope again that well-born Men may ſhine:</l>
               <l>The meaneſt, in your Nature, mild and good,</l>
               <l>The Noble reſt ſecured in your Blood.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For when our Troubl'd Country call'd you forth,</l>
               <l>Your Noble <hi>Courage</hi> and your Matchleſs <hi>Worth</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Dazling the Eyes of all that did pretend,</l>
               <l>To fierce Contention gave a proſperous End.</l>
               <l>No ſooner You, GREAT SIR, the Throne aſcend,</l>
               <l>But our Diſorders ceaſe, and all things mend.</l>
               <l>As if your Royal Touch were only ſure</l>
               <l>The true <hi>King's Evil</hi> of the Realm to Cure.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'Twas not Ambition ſpurr'd our Soveraign on</l>
               <l>To ſeize the Scepter, and aſſume the Crown;</l>
               <l>But like the <hi>Veſtal</hi> Heat, his Martial Fire</l>
               <l>Was ſuch as true <hi>Devotion</hi> did inſpire;</l>
               <l>His Zeal for <hi>GOD,</hi> and Pity to Mankind</l>
               <l>Awak'd his Courage, and confirm'd his Mind.</l>
               <l>Religion 'twas, that putting on his ſhield,</l>
               <l>Brought him <hi>Victorious</hi> through a bloodleſs Field;</l>
               <l>His Arms were ſuch, as th' Ancient <hi>Heroes</hi> wore,</l>
               <l>Bequeath'd him by the <hi>God</hi> he does adore.</l>
               <l>And all to ſave three Kingdoms from the Curſe</l>
               <l>Of Lawleſs Rule, and <hi>Romes</hi> Tyrannick Force.</l>
               <l>A Prince-like Pious <hi>Ardour</hi> of Renown,</l>
               <l>To ſeek the <hi>Church's</hi> Triumph in his <hi>own</hi>:</l>
               <l>Which once accompliſh'd under his Command,</l>
               <l>Th' Auguſt and Grateful <hi>Senate</hi> of the Land</l>
               <l>Gave up what <hi>they</hi> had left (who had done ill)</l>
               <l>To Him, that more deſerv'd the <hi>Throne</hi> to fill.</l>
               <l>With equal Love the Generous <hi>King</hi> releas't</l>
               <l>The chiefeſt Impoſt, which the poor oppreſt;</l>
               <l>Which, tho' ſo fair a Branch of publick Store,</l>
               <l>He valu'd not, becauſe it wrong'd the Poor.</l>
               <l>One Landlord to the Houſe, to Chimneys two,</l>
               <l>Seem'd more than was to equal <hi>Juſtice</hi> due;</l>
               <l>He that once lets his Houſe, his Chimney lets,</l>
               <l>There the poor dreſſes what his Labour gets;</l>
               <l>Hard, double-Pay for that from, whence he eats.</l>
               <l>Or if through Poverty it be not paid,</l>
               <l>For Cruelty to tear away the ſingle Bed,</l>
               <l>On which the poor Man reſts his wearied Head,</l>
               <l>At once deprives him of his Reſt and Bread.</l>
               <l>But ſuch <hi>Injustice</hi> He would not Command,</l>
               <l>Who came by <hi>Juſtice</hi> to relieve the Land;</l>
               <l>Nor would he have an opulent Land ſupply</l>
               <l>Th' Expence of State by grinding Cruelty.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus the vext World to find repoſe, at laſt</l>
               <l>Into <hi>Auguſtus</hi> Arms her ſelf did caſt.</l>
               <l>As <hi>England</hi> now with equal Toyls oppreſt,</l>
               <l>Her wearied Head did on Your Boſome reſt.</l>
               <l>Then let the Muſes with ſuch Notes as theſe,</l>
               <l>Inſtruct us what belongs unto our Peace.</l>
               <l>Here in low ſtrains your milder Deeds we ſing,</l>
               <l>Hereafter we will <hi>Bayes</hi> and <hi>Olive</hi> bring</l>
               <l>To Crown your Head, while you in Triumph ride</l>
               <l>On Vanquiſh'd Nations, and the Sea beſtride;</l>
               <l>While all your <hi>Neighbouring Princes</hi> unto You,</l>
               <l>Like <hi>Ioſeph's Sheaves,</hi> pay Reverence, and bow.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>LONDON, <hi>Printed for</hi> R. Taylor <hi>near</hi> Stationers-Hall, <hi>in the Year, MDCLXXXIX.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
